[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
at collide we know end users are it
admins most significant untapped
resources and key to solving the most
challenging to fix security issues
including instructing developers to set
passphrases on unencrypted ssh keys
finding plaintext two-factor backup
codes and teaching end users how to
store them securely convincing employees
to uninstall evil browser extensions
that may sell their browser history
visit collide.com se radio to sign up
today that's
kolide.com sc radio
enter your email when prompted to
receive your free collide gift bundle
after trial activation
you can try collide with all its
features on an unlimited number of
devices for free for 14 days no credit
card required try it out at collide.com
sc radio
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm akshay manchali my guest today is
juan vernon and we'll be talking about
his most recent book strategic monoliths
and microservices one is an entrepreneur
developer and software architect with
more than 35 years of experience he's a
leading expert on domain driven design
reactive programming event-driven
architecture and he consults and trains
people all over the world in his areas
of expertise one was previously here on
sc radio to talk about reactive
programming with actor model in episode
49 juan welcome back to the show thank
you very much and uh thanks for having
me so let's jump right into the book
what is the key motivation behind it and
briefly what is the message that you're
trying to get across to the reader yeah
so my experience is like you said
more than three decades probably
approaching four decades and
what i've seen over the years is that
there are some very good teams that that
work well together with executive
management with
thought leaders in you know visionaries
and so forth and
there are other teams who seem to be
completely separated from from that kind
of active engagement with business
business vision and
when i have seen
and worked in those environments with a
strong relationship between business and
technology
i
generally see very good results and
so
my motivation isn't trying to surface
this
knowledge and to kind of
set a bar for people to achieve within
strategic initiatives
innovation and
to use examples from
around at least the technology
industries to basically motivate people
to
that they can succeed in the same ways
and use some of the techniques and
you know whether it's engineering
techniques or
innovation through
discovery based learning experimentation
and things like that and try to make
others aware of it
and i think what's really unique about
the book is that we are
addressing
c-level executives senior vps vps chief
architects
directors
and so forth
just as equally as we are solution
architects enterprise architects
programmers and so forth aspiring
architects because you know there's just
a big lack
in this kind of formulation between you
know the business and technology and
i think that it has a chance to help a
lot of companies so what is this general
disconnect that you see between say
business and technology or business and
how they actually run the business and
how does that actually lead to problems
or missed opportunities
working in domain-driven design for
a number of years and and really having
a pretty international exposure to
clients for the past 10 years or so
what i find is that software developers
like to complain about the business not
that they like to but basically they say
we can't engage with the business
because they're unavailable we don't
know who the domain experts are they
won't talk to us they won't whatever
and
in reality what i see
is
like in a workshop i will become
the domain expert right in a set of
scenarios where we're in essence working
for a fictitious startup and we're
trying to innovate together
and the exercises that we go through
really lend themselves to
interfacing with the business and when i
walk around to different teams and i
suggest or even ask you know do you need
my help as the domain expert co-founder
of the company right do you need to help
anything that i could clarify
anything in the business
vision
and so forth and inevitably the
developers will say no we got this
and that's a huge problem i mean they're
all
they're they are there
to learn ddd
and one of the basic premises of ddd is
that you're going to engage with the
business and i don't know like why is it
that
that message doesn't go all the way to
the
top floor you know with with these
developers i mean before we do a single
exercise i'm already telling them that
they have to do this and they don't and
okay
maybe that's sort of a learned behavior
a survival instinct or something like
that but they're given every opportunity
to work with someone you know myself who
represents the business and has their
every success
in mind and heart and they still
hesitate
now on the other hand i do know that
business people very often just get
frustrated
with
engineers technologists and so forth
because the engineers always want to
kind of talk down to them condescend
with big technical terminology and
there's always this translation between
what the business says and what that
means to engineering instead of finding
a common ground so
there's a lot of problem with that a lot
of frustration
between business and technology
engineering and
i think that a lot of that that you know
since there is so much someone just
needs to
like
bring this up
to
high enough level where people are
forced to see it right and then we give
suggestions in the book to
as we do when we consult and train how
to overcome these kinds of challenges
and um
so hopefully by making a a sort of first
class concern
then
others are going to say yeah yeah we do
this we do absolutely have that problem
and it's necessary for us to do
something about it in general if you're
coming from engineering or even from the
business you
normally anticipate some amount of
change to your underlying technology to
support the business so you said you
know communication is one of those
barriers towards change but are there
other barriers that you see that
prohibit change or results in change in
a suboptimal way that results in what
you call mud systems in the book it may
sound strange
maybe it doesn't but i find that when
i walk in to a client
not all
but
enough
and some of the clients that i engage
with you would be maybe surprised just
about them how much kind of fiefdom
there is around certain areas of the
technology and and chief architects for
example
and and these are companies who have
multiple chief architects right and in
different divisions and so forth and
they will be very resistant to change
first of all they think that they don't
have
any problems
but the technical leadership has already
identified problems but they highly
resist any change whatsoever because
then they sort of have to admit that
they were wrong but i don't
i don't think that
there's much value in viewing it that
way like okay everybody's wrong a lot of
times in software
so we have to view this as an
opportunity to course correct and make
things better so i don't i don't know
why
people view it like that their job is in
danger or something because they have to
you know renew something that's 20 or 25
years old
instead of just continuing to build on
it and cause more
atrophy and and so forth and
that that they just need to sort of you
know step up say yeah you're right we
need to do this in fact what i've
actually seen is that those who resist
the kind of forward thinking you know
let's let's change things
senior you know executive leadership
technical leadership will actually say
well you actually may not have a future
with this company if you're not willing
to make a change so they kind of think
that they're preventing a bad
path but they're actually causing one by
resisting
so that's just you know that's the
resistance to change but then once you
get to the point where people say yeah
we have to change
a lot of what i see is that people
expect that this is just going to
disappear you know all the problems that
they have are going to disappear within
a few months i mean even talking about a
year from now
a lot of them will think whoa you know
what why would it take so long well look
it's taken you
years
decades maybe a score or two of years to
get where you are you're not gonna just
jump out of that crystal
clean you know for within a few months
so
there's just a lot of reasons for this
and in general a lot of times the skill
level of developers
is really not very good and they they
get a little bit
jaded i guess or just um demotivated
from the fact that they haven't
previously been able to really make a
significant change so this will just
kind of put them into a let's collect a
paycheck zone and i think on the other
hand you also have the tendency to maybe
adapt changes that may not be necessary
and i think parts of the book kind of
address that in terms of
going after something that's new and
shiny for example and so let me ask you
this do you think monoliths are bad or
as opposed to say microservices are they
good do you have to say about that yeah
and and just before i answer the
specific question yes
many very bright technology people
are really
chasing new technologies you know bright
shiny whatever but
they my idea and that i've you know
confirmed by others experts that i've
spoken with
they say that engineers have to be
challenged and if they're not challenged
with the business problem they're going
to challenge themselves with technical
problems to solve right technical
challenges
and so that will lead many to
you know want to
use technologies in places where they
don't really
need them but
hey you know we can maybe it's open
source a lot of things are open source
let's just use it it doesn't really cost
the company much although it does in the
end so to address your specific
questions though about um are monoliths
bad are microservices good probably for
the past
seven years i'm going to say at least
the word monolith has just gotten a
really bad you know reputation
and
i don't think that
it's really fair
but i i think what people generally mean
when they say the word monolith
is big ball of mud monolith right the
legacy system that is just
out of sorts um
has been subject to
expedient changes for
you know week after week month after
month year after year and the
architecture if there ever was really a
purposeful architecture has long
disappeared or blended into this muddy
kind of
situation and
so this is really
where the
the term monolith has become
synonymous with bad software
but a monolith itself
is not bad in fact probably most
companies should be using monolithic
architecture rather than microservices
any given company can use both make good
uses of them
but you know to to address the second
part of that question or the second
question
are microservices good
they can be but you know the
microservice itself is not
going to solve your problems no more
than bringing
kubernetes into your enterprise is going
to solve your problems or
kafka right i mean these are just tools
and and they're very you know cool they
serve you know a very
excellent
set of you know a purpose with excellent
qualities about them but those things in
themselves are not going to
really solve many problems so
microservices are the same way and in
fact microservices can end up causing
more problems than they solve
and that is generally
the case when a microservice is seen as
a specific size as in like lines of code
you know there's been
i would say probably a lot more
emphasis on the 100 line of code
microservice you know this is what makes
a good microservice
and i'm not sure
why that ever came up because first of
all depending on the programming
language the number of lines of code
could be vastly different for the same
amount of behavior you know of solution
being offered
the other thing is that even
so you know so if i have a micro service
that's 150 lines of code does that make
it bad
others say you know 400 lines of code
i've heard that i've heard a thousand
lines of code
the thing is those are all just very
you know subjective like
then
you know what am i targeting these
numbers and
instead of using those kinds of
measurements if you will we suggest
using domain-driven design as
the first
step in identifying a microservice
and using ddd-bounded context as the
means to do that and what we
basically emphasize is determine what
your ubiquitous language is within a
mounted context and that is you know by
modeling that becomes the size of your
micro service which is
who cares if it's a thousand lines or 2
000 lines or
or 300 lines or 100 right it's whatever
it needs to be to express that
ubiquitous language as a model so if you
kind of target that it's a great place
to start and then you're not using any
of these arbitrary size determinations
and shooting for targets that have no
real practical meaning
and i think it helps a lot so yeah
anything anything in software has
trade-offs microservices can be good but
they introduce a set of challenges as
well
monoliths
can be good but they also introduce a
set of trade-offs um challenges with
them so we always have to look at what
are we trying what problem are we trying
to solve what solution do we need to
come up with and so let's have a
purposeful architecture based on that
and the configuration of our team and
the rate of change in certain areas of
the software and um
maybe a monolith will work out in a lot
of cases or maybe a lot of the solution
is in a monolith and we break out a few
micro services because of the rate of
change
and i also want to just caution people
you know i've heard this a lot about you
know if you want to increase performance
and and scalability and you know a lot
of you know these
quality attributes right so you're
you're introducing these quality
attributes
actually performance is not a good idea
to to have in mind if you're going with
microservices right because you
introduce the network in there that's
going to
greatly reduce performance
okay we are using the cloud a lot we are
doing distributed computing a lot
but if you really don't have to there's
no sense in introducing the network
and besides the fact that it's not just
performance but actually okay maybe you
are looking for scale but on the other
hand you you introduce a higher
probability of
failure right network partitions just
whatever out you know indeterminism in
in message receiving and and things like
that so you know everything comes with a
set of trade-offs and you just have to
choose the positive trade-offs that fit
your needs and they should outweigh the
negative trade-offs and that's
generally purposeful architecture but
the main emphasis is strategic
innovation right and when it comes to
the sort of decisions about say
spinning off something into a micro
service breaking it down in the book you
mentioned something called conveys law
that influences interface design so can
you describe that and how that actually
influences change how that influences
architecture over time
so
basically what mel conway said is you
know in this nutshell is
that
software
or any any system
that is designed is constrained to
reflect or
have a representation of the
communication structure of the
organization that created it and that
doesn't mean necessarily the whole big
organization like if you know if you're
a fortune 10 company it doesn't mean
that that entire fortune 10 company has
an impact necessarily directly on one
system that's somewhere you know in that
large organization but the direct
organization that is used to develop
that will have their communication
structure
you know will be reflected in that
system design now one thing that some
people will sort of very kind of
trivially almost naively say is well
what conway's law says is if you decide
to use three teams to develop
a system then there will be three
subsystems and i think that's a gross
oversimplification and in fact that it's
not even true especially when you're
developing with a microservices mindset
i mean any given team could own multiple
bounded contacts
and you know so i i just kind of throw
that part of the
understanding you know like i just throw
it out the window it's it's not worth
considering to me
but what it really is saying is for
whatever teams you put together
those teams must communicate really well
in order for their design
to
reflect
you know well on their communication
because it will right it'll either
reflect good communication or poor
communication and
mel conway also way back then said okay
so
since most systems don't have the best
design after the first say
initial iterations the first version if
you will of the system then
organizations should be flexible and be
be willing to basically reorganize teams
to improve the communication in order to
improve the subsystems within the system
right so
i appreciate that some companies have
come up with kind of catchy names for
this kind of you know maneuver
as it's referred to but mel conway gave
us those answers so long ago right you
know whatever now 54 years ago so it's
it's pretty amazing that he had not only
recognized the problem but held the
solution and now 50 years later
companies are just saying yeah well this
is how you should do this and this
should do that and it's just basically
what he said so long ago and yeah it's
really important very very important and
of course domain driven design
is really chiefly about communication
and learning right it's it's about
discovering experimentation and this is
how we learn and how we learn quickly
so
the better we communicate the quicker we
learn
the better our systems will be the the
less expensive they will be so there's a
lot of benefits to recognizing conway's
law and then setting our teams up for
the best possible opportunity to succeed
within that so you mentioned bounded
contexts and i want to get to that but
given what you just said if i'm say a
software architect or i'm some sort of a
technology leader how do you approach a
particular problem by modeling the sort
of like communications between people
how do you go about modeling the
existing structures of an organization
along with the technology that exists
today in order to support you know
whatever incoming change requests are
coming into you
how do we solve problems with bounded
context one of the first things that a
large organization can do
and again limit
the area to the problem space where you
have identified we need to
solve this
scientific you know innovation
problem and this will be strategically
beneficial to us what systems do we need
to use
let's take an inventory of what exists
and what we wish was there
or what we need to have that
is missing so kind of the gaps
and
you can use business capabilities right
you can kind of look for business
capabilities that you know that you have
and look for the areas of software that
provide those business capabilities
in a very
large enterprise with a number of legacy
systems those capabilities
are very likely
not
necessarily even constrained to a single
big ball of mud monolith they could be
kind of spread around right like okay we
integrate just think of
shipping for example
how does shipping happen from
an e-commerce perspective i know this is
not necessarily an insurance problem but
it just comes to mind
where is your shipping logic
in you know your shipping model in
a legacy system it's probably in five
different places at least but you can
still look at those five places as one
context or
one sub-domain
and this helps you to sort of
reason about the problem even though
it's not one thing it's not one
convenient place to go
you can still create that kind of
illusion and that might give you even a
hint toward yeah well maybe we want it
maybe we want even in real software to
make that look as if those five places
are one place so maybe that's a new
service that just provides some kind of
integration for us right
and there are different ways to do that
but then we may have some well-designed
services and systems and those might
represent in themselves bounded context
but the real sort of definition
of a bounded context is a sphere of
knowledge and
a place where a model
and a language
a human language that is spoken and
understood by a team
and a relatively small team of
individuals where they are innovating
this is
a place where we are going
to design and implement our software in
this kind of contextual boundary right
so think of
if you have a a yard with a fence
and your neighbors have yards with
fences think of each of those as a
different context right you all have
maybe grass growing in inside your yard
inside your fence
but what does grass mean to your family
is it a place where your kids roll
around and play or is it a place where
you know someone in the family just
loves to manicure the lawn and don't
ever step on that right and so you can
think of those as different contexts
even though they're they all have grass
maybe even very similar kinds of grass
but the context of the use of that yard
and the purpose of that yard why it
exists is different so think of various
areas of the business where you use the
same words right like policy
we use policy all over the place in an
insurance company but what does policy
mean here versus what a policy means
over there right
and even though they may share some data
between them and even share some
terminology between them they're
generally speaking going to have
different meanings and so domain driven
design uses the bounded context to
emphasize that we don't have to agree on
the definitions of things right of the
areas of software and especially in
specific models right we don't have to
agree therefore
we're going to recognize those
differences and bound them
in a context where we can have a very
you know certain understanding of what
those meanings are and what what are the
purposes what are the business rules
around it so it encapsulates all of that
uh knowledge essentially in a way that
you can then use to see how much can be
reused where it fits how it can change
etc is that one way of actually using it
absolutely yes that is the idea starting
from this sort of like bounded context i
think you also talk about spheres of
knowledge at various levels like for
example if you have to go back to the
example of yards and how you want to
model that the the scope of where that
utility of say your garden ends is
something that you talk in the book in
terms of actually modeling that in order
to figure out you know how things should
actually fit in so can you elaborate
about how you
speak about spheres of knowledge the
scope of it and how that influences your
design or how that should influence your
design rather
so
sphere of knowledge actually is
one of the
four or so
numbered definitions of the word domain
if you look in merriam-webster's
dictionary so if you look there under
the word domain
there are like four
primary definitions and i think the
third one is a sphere of knowledge and
domain can mean like a kingdom kind of
domain or a governmental domain an
ownership of property and things like
that
and in a sense you can see some overlap
in that
but the first primary definition
that we use for domain-driven design is
this sphere of knowledge right this is a
place where a specific area of expertise
exists and the people that we have to
have conversations with or you know
including us right so everybody
who has this
kind of either business expertise
in this area
or software expertise in order to
implement this properly and be a good
listener and be a good collaborator and
communicator
we are creating a sphere of knowledge
and the longer that we work together in
the more valuable conversations we have
the more we learn
and so while an event storming may start
out being
like a really big picture across
multiple subsystems or pre-existing
systems that we will use to
create this new
innovative
area
when we boil it down to that sphere of
knowledge than our event storming and
our scenarios that we discuss and any
kinds of
conversations that we have whether it's
in written documents or or just spoken
words in a meeting which probably are
the most frequent and then we we
actually take these ideas from our minds
and we communicate them with each other
and we finally have this sort of shared
understanding then you know we can write
tests and software and then make our our
software adhere to those tests and and
work you know to succeed
to test green in other words
well that is
all part of the sphere of knowledge so
that is a context right
and
actually to to make a further point
generally speaking that sphere of
knowledge is also a sub-domain in the
entire
problem domain right so now when we're
looking just at the areas of the
enterprise
or
whatever you like to call it right that
that will
contribute to the success of this
innovation
those various areas that we will work
with and include in this
initiative are
all in some way or another
separate subdomains right or or at least
contribute to the separate subdomains
and so you can look at
this landscape
as being like okay this is our whole
world right now this is kind of our you
know whole world this problem domain and
within that problem domain we have sub
sub domains and some of those sub
domains will be core
right they will be places where we're
really innovating and in essence making
a big impact on the industry or that
we're working in i want to switch gears
a little bit into transformation
of software so in your book you talk
about purposeful architecture and ways
to transform
monoliths into microservices or starting
to build microservices correctly so i
want to switch gears to that
let's first start with the monolith
right so how do you build monoliths
correctly or what would influence you to
say
monolith is the right design when you're
starting from nothing
and what would be the right way to
actually approach that problem our
recommendation is actually to start with
monoliths so it's actually not even that
you're starting with a monolith like
that you're necessarily even planning to
use a monolith long term but by
eliminating the network
in
most of the integrations within this
solution that you're creating with new
software right so this we're talking
about new software then you would use
major
modules
within the monolith
to separate the different bounded
contexts so think of a monolith that has
maybe like seven major modules
and we in essence treat those
modules
as if
they are
in separate
services on the network but they're not
right but in other words that's how much
kind of like very definite separation
that we have between them and so our
motivation in doing that is to make
certain that we are not
creating
dependencies
across bounded contexts
you know like strong coupling that would
be very difficult to break
later if we decided to
sort of carve out one of those bounded
contacts or a few of them and turn them
into separate microservices
so there are reasons to do that and i
mentioned that before such one of the
best reasons is rate of change right
is this context changing more often
than the other six
that are in this monolith
so that's
that's a big part of it
um
but yeah the using modularity and
i've heard some interesting feedback on
this in fact i've had some discussions
about it and some people think
that if you're starting out with a
monolith you you will certainly not want
to um create
multiple bounded contexts within there
but you'll you'll just want everything
to just
sort of allow it to be jumbled up and i
i truly cannot understand
why that would be a purposeful
initiative because it's the very thing
that we're trying to avoid is
the big ball of mud and
you're just
absolutely doing that is moving quickly
in the direction of a big ball mod if
you if you just
say that we're limiting our discipline
in the modularity for
contextual separation
it doesn't mean that we have to
introduce
heavyweight
you know for example messaging systems
there are
several lightweight messaging systems
that we can use between you know to
communicate between the bounded contexts
or we can even use
you know in essence what would be
similar to rest or
so
you know but but it doesn't have to be
rest i mean it can be rest from a
an api perspective of using
um
you know
post
um get
put delete kind of thing you know
um but it doesn't have to be over http
right it doesn't have to be
over tcp on the network
can just be
um
method invocations but they're but
they're loosely coupled
and they might even have use um
multi-threading
just to you know keep
things very separated and
well now we're getting into another area
of reactive but that that is basically
the motivation of a well
modularized monolith
now again
we're not even making a decision yet
if we should use any microservices at
all or if all of those
modules should be turned into
microservices but what we're doing is
we're saying we want to innovate first
we want to
have
you know
high
iterative
and incremental
value delivery deliveries in these
multiple bounded contexts
and we're purposely leaving out the
network right now in fact you might even
just use in-memory databases and so
forth you you don't you know this is
where we're just trying to get the model
right
where we're we're trying to understand
okay solve the business problem first
because when you take it the other way
around and you say okay hey you know
we're going to start
doing micro services tell you what you
spin up you know something on azure and
and i'll spin up something on google
cloud platform and
and you do something on aws because hey
we need multi-cloud right and that and
oh my goodness you know do you know do
right i mean anybody listening to that
should just say anybody that's starting
out a project in that way
just seems really immature to me it's
just a the wrong time to introduce
things like that so introduce those
things later when you know that they're
absolutely necessary but get the
business innovation for first i think in
what you're saying is when you're trying
to model it at that level you're also
disconnected from the specifics of
implementation choices right like where
this is going to run or what language
i'm going to write this in you're really
exploring what the interfaces should be
between your bounded contexts or are you
also saying that you should go a little
bit deeper well i mean you go deeper as
you learn more but for example
some people will just say well let's
introduce a nosql database you know
but i don't like is that the right thing
to do right now how do you know that
right so
so first of all just create if you think
a nosql database
um works then create a simple
you know
interface for a nosql database which is
basically a hash map or a hash table
underneath
and just see how that works right
um
and
you know but
if you find later oh look well it's
really hard to query that
it doesn't you know it doesn't support
the kinds of queries we'd like well what
should we do about that should we
introduce cqrs or well that you know it
seems like a little bit of overhead here
we don't really need
that kind of thing but maybe just a
relational database in this case would
work better for us right it would just
be simpler and maybe this is a
a some supporting software that isn't
even core
for example and we just decide to say
let's not burn too much cash
on on those kinds of expenses right
and let's just keep it really simple and
hey for the for the scale and the
performance that we have
10 000 transactions per second is way
more than we need and and i'm just
speaking for
sort of like the the 95 or so of all
software projects of course there's that
five or maybe even just one percent of
software that needs you know those off
the charts
kinds of
scale and and throughput but i'm just
talking about like
for most right 10 000 transactions per
second that you can get from
quite easily in fact from postgres and
especially on the cloud
right then
then um just avoid those kind of
really heavyweight decisions
at first or things that will just
complicate
the overall solution but i mean even if
you have that sort of need where you
need a hundred thousand transactions per
second i
feel like that might be its own bounded
context that provides that layer that
provides that service that others should
be consuming
or do you think that even there it's
just simply not necessary for you to go
down that path of exploring you know
what might fit the performance or
scalability needs
i don't generally think of a bounded
context in a very technical way in other
words should a bounded context be
primarily for persistence
there are some ways of using bounded
context for a sort of messaging switch
or router but those those have
additional purposes but i wouldn't think
of having a separate bounded context
that would just provide persistence
so what about existing software you
might have an existing monolith that
maybe it's not completely unmaintainable
maybe it has some modules but how do you
go about
trying to prepare that into
microservice why would you do that one
and how do you actually
go about breaking it down so that you
can separate things out while also
supporting the monolith along the way
well assuming that
we have started with a well-modularized
monolith right so we're developing a new
system and
we have like i said just as an example
we have seven different bounded contexts
in a monolith
when those separations are very clean
between the seven
then taking one out of that monolith and
turning it into its own separate
deployment unit and introducing the
network is
pretty straightforward i mean you will
have to introduce the network you will
have to decide things like well okay are
we going to communicate
with rest to this other context or will
we use asynchronous messaging or you
know a messaging mechanism whatever it
happens to be the network will be
involved but you've already got those
what we would call a ports and adapters
architecture you've already got those
adapters
figured out you just need to change the
technology that's underneath them and if
you design them correctly there won't be
you know leaky
abstractions i guess if you have the
clear boundaries you could always just
take that apart and then use the same
interface over say the network but what
if you don't right everything is a
entangled mess and
is it always better to just throw away
everything and start from scratch or is
there like a generally good way where
you can go in a purposeful way where you
know what you want as a microservice
what you want to remain in the monolith
and actually
find a path to untangling that mess of
your software just for example yes there
there are ways to
take a big ball of mud monolith and
redesign slash refactor that and we
provide several different approaches
for different tools and patterns and so
forth for doing that and you know it
doesn't happen overnight and there's
going to be a lot of work to it and
generally speaking it means introducing
unit tests where there never were unit
tests before and you know so it can be a
lot of work now the total throwaway not
that you completely throw away but just
think of these you know many many
financial services companies whether
they're banks or insurance companies or
whatever they happen to be in and they
are just you know laden with cobalt i
mean no disrespect but there are a lot
of organizations that we work with that
are just
very burdened with these 40 50 year old
systems that are running on mainframes
with cobalt and it's getting very
difficult to find
developers it's it's not news to anyone
with experience in that but so they're
not throw away you do have to probably
mine a number of not probably you have
to mine a number of business rules
out of their calculations you know
whatever those kinds of heavy lifting
things but one advantage is that
sometimes
those
cobalt systems are so old that a large
number of
the business rules are now obsolete
right
had one company that i i think they
identified something like
75 or 80 percent of all
business rules since the mid 1970s
no longer had any
relevance so
now can you imagine not
studying that and understanding and you
actually go to the effort to sort of
port out all of those
business rules calculations and whatever
and and then a few months after you've
done that someone says we don't even use
that anymore right
that as in like 100 000 lines of code or
more so or millions
so
yeah so it's not easy but
definitely you're you're looking to do
full system replacement for those kinds
of situations but if you have like even
you know like a legacy java system or a
legacy ruby
ruby on rails system or
net or something like that and there are
plenty of those you know it sounds funny
because i was still relatively young
when these technologies came to
existence and it's sort of funny to
think of java having legacy systems but
then you remember oh yeah i've been
using java for like more than 20 years
now so
so yeah there are plenty of legacy
systems there but the fact that you can
reshape those with a lot of effort
yeah you you can salvage
some things out of there but it's mostly
going to be
kind of restructuring
as in finding new modules
and trying to bring the the cohesive
classes if you will or objects together
into one area and call that a bounded
context now right that's that's what
you're trying to achieve and you
typically have to do that sort of like
one context at a time or even if you're
doing many at once you're sort of doing
a piecemeal and as you maybe it's as
you're making changes anyway they're
driven by
you know like the business says this has
to change or we have a bug that we need
to fix in here you can use that
opportunity to
go in and start cleaning up that area so
while you're there why not write some
tests why not look for a new module for
that and put it with the other cohesive
parts of that language and now you're
kind of slowly creating
at least modularity if not bounded
context within there
okay that's great about existing
software but let's say you're trying to
start something new but
you want to build microservices maybe
because you have lots of people lots of
very clear responsibilities and roles
where things are separated so maybe it
just looks like a microservices
architecture would be better and if so
how do you approach that problem how do
you approach modeling your problem space
so that you build micro services in a
way that does not introduce extreme
complexity but also allows you to change
in the future
there's really determined purposeful
effort being put into this so
when you know that you're going to
develop microservices and you know that
this is happening as a core effort
then how do you do that well and as we
said before or as i said before and as
we say in the book look for
capabilities
look for bounded contexts and bounded
contexts are going to be in the areas of
expertise of spheres of knowledge right
so that this is where you have to talk
to certain business people to understand
the rules and the mental model that they
have and how to
formulate
a software model from this
and this is a great place to start for
microservices
but again
if you develop the
well-modularized monolith we also show
in that 11th chapter how to go from a
well-modularized monolith to
microservices so you know both of those
though are using bounded context as the
driver
and again you know just going back to
what a bounded context is a sphere of
knowledge a place where a team has
conversation
you know directed conversation
purposeful
experimentation and looking you know to
learn and learn rapidly
this is a bounded context and when a
microservice is deployed
or i should say
maybe that when a bounded context is
deployed as a microservice then that is
a a very reasonable goal to have and
will very often work out well
now the opposite of that
is you know like a micro service
that only
for example
it just creates a new entity of a
certain type then you have another
microservice that updates
an entity of the same type that you have
a microserver to to create right i mean
this is the sort of granularity where
i'm saying danger zone you know that you
really don't want to be
down on those weeds
from the beginning for sure and
hopefully you won't end up there even in
the end
so you may need to take certain
components maybe entity types or ddd
maybe what we would refer to as an
aggregate and some of those you may need
to break out because the business rules
around those change more often and it
might make sense to just isolate
those areas of change so that you can
deploy quickly right and you don't you
don't get sort of
the other parts of the same context
don't get in your critical path and in
your way of quicker delivery
but still they are part of the same
bounded context right logically speaking
the purpose of this is to to maintain
this sphere of knowledge and the team
stays together even though now they have
multiple
units of software components to to
deploy i do think that sometimes if
you're that isolated maybe
you could end up doing something some
other team is doing does this lead to
some sort of siloing when you say
you want to actually create this sphere
of knowledge this bounded context and
then they go and build what they're
building but does that lead to
siloing does that lead to
repetition of something someone else is
doing maybe it does and how do you break
that well in some organizations you may
never know
if that happens literally right i mean
it's one thing to know that it happens
it's a completely other thing to
be like completely oblivious to the fact
that you know that other 100 000
person you know part of the organization
did this very similar to us and we could
have reused it but we didn't even know
that it existed and they don't know that
we exist but one thing to remember is
that
don't repeat yourself or the dry
principle right is
is about knowledge
so
don't repeat yourself means don't repeat
the same knowledge
around a system it doesn't mean
that code cannot be repeated i know that
may sound like sort of a
you know a contradiction but it's really
not because
maybe
the code that exists in multiple places
is just
like we you know we have the same
attributes or properties on a class
right on an object but
we're careful not to leak
knowledge across bounded contexts so
this is where again you may have
something named policy
in two or three different places or five
different places
and that policy will all they'll all
have a policy id and this will all go
you know all those ids point back to
sort of that system of record where the
policy first existed
and maybe some of the attributes are you
know like what's the type of policy or
what is you know this
um these kinds of sharing of things but
that is not
um knowledge that's being repeated
that's just
data and
you know necessary
repetition that that we're using
so first of all if we if we are not
repeating
knowledge then there isn't really
a don't repeat yourself another
principle to use though is just simply
that dry
is
a context to context
concern so
even if you have to repeat some things
in another bounded context
do so without making
um
a real silo and this is sort of the
pattern um or the the
context mapping
approach that's known as separate ways
it's it's like okay we could integrate
but the payoff for this integration the
the complexity versus the
the gain that we will get from it just
isn't worth it so we're going to go
separate ways and this is where you know
we may repeat something but we are we
are really certain that we're and
make concerted effort not to create
silos in that case so if you don't
repeat the knowledge then i guess in
some sense the
underlying
business problem is not solved in two
different places by repetition so you
don't really drift across what should
really happen for the business
yeah one way to think about that is
for example when calculating risks
so let's say that we have a bounded
context around
calculating risk
and we have we have another
bounded context
for calculating rate as in what what is
the premium that will be paid for
example for this automobile insurance
well we don't want
the rate system or the the risk system
um
leaking
into the
the rate system and we don't want you
know the money
kinds of things
falling back into the risk system so
that's where you would have a definite
you know like repeating
of knowledge
so
but you will still be talking about you
know you'll still be working on the same
um
policy well it's at that point it's an
application right so someone has applied
for insurance
so you'll still be looking at the same
pieces of data
but for example when you calculate the
risk that risk will be passed on
along with the application to
the
to the rate calculator in that case so
yeah you definitely want to keep those
two things separate but the fact that we
have to
reference the same properties
in
the application
and that we will use the rate
calculation outcome or the i'm sorry the
risk out
calculation outcome
in
rate doesn't mean that we're repeating
knowledge it just means that we have to
use that
data and those attributes to accomplish
what we need to do in calculating a rate
one last uh question is uh
what stage do you make decisions about
exactly what technology you use to
actually build these let's say you do go
down the microservices path as we were
just talking about
at what point you say
these are the technology choices that
we're going to make
do you actually go for something that's
more homogeneous where every
microservices may be written in the same
language
versus in different
languages maybe they're completely
independent what are the trade-offs and
at what point do you make those
decisions
well that's a really cultural sort of
decision to make and i think it that
kind of decision
[Music]
to me it's sort of like well if you're
amazon
maybe you want to give complete autonomy
to a team and and say you know if you
want to use some
sort of almost unknown language like
maybe you even wrote your own compiler
so i don't i don't know what the rules
are but in other words it could
be to that extreme where people are just
like way out
on the razor's edge of something
and maybe to amazon it really doesn't
matter because their services are so
small that if someone comes along and
goes like oh well they left the company
and nobody's here to support that
compiler let's rewrite it in
blah right
um
no big deal but
you know if you're in um
you know the
the
startup company with
um
you know you're hiring your
70th
um employee
and
you've already introduced five or six
different languages across microservices
that sounds pretty risky to me you know
it just seems like
like do you really want to create that
kind of culture
early
and what what are the risks of
you know like if someone would leave if
an individual or two would leave
what's
what's the probability of hiring
someone in their place
but
it's even really more than that it's
like just choose the right language for
the job so they're you know like for
example python
even though i
think that you know python is quite an
expensive language to use for runtime
right it's not really a very efficient
language
but if there are and there are tons of
machine learning type libraries for
python well you're just going to use
python for machine learning kinds of
things right so
i i mean it makes sense
um so even a startup with hiring their
70th employee just around the corner
they're going to use that
they're going to use python they're
going to use you know whatever maybe
kotlin maybe
c sharp f sharp whatever but
um
sort of make sure that
it's not a single
engineer you know kind of
bus factor kind of um problem that you
could face and and as long as you have
a number of individuals that have
expertise in those languages then
it's really not a problem yeah that
makes sense and one last question to
conclude what do you think people at
various levels
should be doing to
go towards purposeful architecture now
there's a lot of things that we've
talked about that's mostly about say in
the technical leaders maybe even
executives but also individual
contributors and regular software
professionals what do you think they can
take away from this book in order to
move towards say purposeful architecture
in their day-to-day jobs
just completely shift gears
to innovation
as
you know software as a strategy software
for delivering innovation
and
when your mind shifts to that
and you're having fun solving difficult
business problems right like
then you don't need
kubernetes and who knows what right to
to be that
that sort of like feather in your cap
because you're just having too much fun
like doing heavy lifting for the
business and really doing innovative
things
then the architecture that you choose
will sort of fall in place because
you're
you're you're already challenged enough
um
with
you know the business challenge and the
business innovation that you don't want
to in any way make your
delivery any more complex because hey
that's just going to take away from the
fun of innovating right
and i think that so many software
developers are very very capable
of being
you know
not necessarily great inventors
but great innovators um
and there is a difference right
invention means something sort of from
nothing
a very original idea innovation means
taking something that exists and making
it much better so
you know so i i think many software
developers can
can offer that kind of high class
capabilities to a business and that's
going to make for a really great
partnership between business and
software developers
one it's been wonderful talking to you
thanks for coming back again
thank you this is akshay munchali for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening